So here's the same query you saw earlier.
إذن ها هو الاستعلام ذاته الذي رأيتموه قبل ذلك.
Now let's break it down a little bit.
فهيا نقوم بتفكيكه بعض الشيء.
Like we saw before, whenever we want to fetch data out of the database,
كما رأينا من قبل، كلما أردنا استخراج البيانات من قاعدة البيانات،
we'll begin our query with the keyword select.
سنبدأ الاستعلام بالكلمة الأساسية select.
Then we say, which columns we want to see in the result?
ثم نقول، ما الأعمدة التي نريد رؤيتها في النتيجة؟
And then what tables they're going to come from?
وبعد ذلك، ما الجداول التي ستُستمد منها؟
Then we have this where thing at the end.
ثم نحصل على المكان حيث ينتمي الشيء في النهاية.
That's the restriction, and it says what kind of rows we want to see.
وذلك هو القيد، وينص على نوع الصفوف التي نريد رؤيتها.
Here, we only want to see rows where the species is gorilla, but
فهنا، نريد فقط رؤية الصفوف حيث تكون الفصيلة هي الغوريلا،
what if we want to restrict on more than one thing?
ولكن ماذا لو أردنا فرض القيد على أكثر من شيء واحد؟
We can do that.
نستطيع القيام بذلك.
SQL supports the boolean and.
يدعم SQL العامل المنطقي and،
Just like python does.
مثل python تمامًا.
If we want to find out the birth date of Max the gorilla, we can do it like this.
وإذا أردنا معرفة تاريخ ميلاد الغوريلا ماكس، فيمكننا فعل ذلك بهذا الشكل.
SQL also supports the or and not operators, also like in python.
كما يدعم SQL العوامل المنطقية or وnot، كما في python أيضًا.
So given what we've just seen, how might we find the names of
إذن بالحصول على ما رأيناه للتو، كيف يمكننا إيجاد أسماء جميع الحيوانات
all of the animals that are not gorillas, and are not named Max?
التي لا تنتمي لفصيلة الغوريلا، والتي لا تسمى ماكس؟
Try that on the next page.
جربوا ذلك في الصفحة التالية.